I want you to imagine this for a moment.
أريدكم أن تتخيلوا هذا للحظة
Two men, Rahul and Rajiv,
رَجُلان: "راؤول" و "راجيف"
living in the same neighborhood,
يعيشان في نفس المنطقة،
from the same educational background, similar occupation,
ولهما نفس المستوى التعليمي ونفس الوظيفة
and they both turn up at their local accident emergency
كلاهما يأتي لمركز الطوارئ المحلي
complaining of acute chest pain.
بشكوى ألم حاد في الصدر.
Rahul is offered a cardiac procedure,
يتم إجراء عملية قلبية لراؤول،
but Rajiv is sent home.
ويتم إرسال راجيف للمنزل.
What might explain the difference in the experience
ماذا يمكن أن يفسّر الفرق في ما حدث
of these two nearly identical men?
لهذين الرَجُلين المتشابهين؟
Rajiv suffers from a mental illness.
راجيف يعاني من مرض نفسي.
The difference in the quality of medical care
الفرق في جودة الخدمة الطبية
received by people with mental illness is one of the reasons
التي يتلقاها المرضى النفسيون هو أحد أسباب
why they live shorter lives
أنهم يعيشون حياة أقصر
than people without mental illness.
من أولئك الذين لا يعانون من مرض نفسي
Even in the best-resourced countries in the world,
حتى في أحسن الدول الغنية في العالم
this life expectancy gap is as much as 20 years.
يصل الفرق بين متوسطي الحياة إلى 20 سنة
In the developing countries of the world, this gap
وفي الدول النامية
is even larger.
يكون الفرق أكبر.
But of course, mental illnesses can kill in more direct ways
لكن بالطبع المرض النفسي يمكن أن يقتل بطرق مباشرة أيضا
as well. The most obvious example is suicide.
وأوضح مثال هو الانتحار
It might surprise some of you here, as it did me,
قد يُدهش بعضكم من ذلك كما دُهشت
when I discovered that suicide is at the top of the list
عندما اكتشفت أن الانتحار هو في أول قائمة
of the leading causes of death in young people
الأسباب الأساسية لموت الشباب
in all countries in the world,
في جميع دول العالم،
including the poorest countries of the world.
حتى أفقر دول العالم
But beyond the impact of a health condition
ولكن ما وراء تأثير الحالة الصحية
on life expectancy, we're also concerned
على متوسط العمر، نحن نهتم
about the quality of life lived.
بمستوى المعيشة أكثر
Now, in order for us to examine the overall impact
والآن من أجل أن نعرف التأثير الكلّي
of a health condition both on life expectancy
للحالة الصحية على متوسط العمر
as well as on the quality of life lived, we need to use
ومستوى المعيشة، نحتاج إلى
a metric called the DALY,
مقياس يسمّى DALY
which stands for a Disability-Adjusted Life Year.
والذي يعني معدل السنة الحياتية للإعاقة.
Now when we do that, we discover some startling things
الآن عندما نقوم بذلك، يمكننا اكتشاف بعض الأشياء المذهلة
about mental illness from a global perspective.
حول المرض النفسي من منظور عالمي.
We discover that, for example, mental illnesses are
نكتشف أنه على سبيل المثال، الأمراض النفسية
amongst the leading causes of disability around the world.
من الأسباب الرئيسية للإعاقة حول العالم.
Depression, for example, is the third-leading cause
الاكتئاب، على سبيل المثال، هو السبب الثالث
of disability, alongside conditions such as
للإعاقة، جنبا إلى جنب مع أمراض مثل
diarrhea and pneumonia in children.
الإسهال والالتهاب الرئوي في الأطفال.
When you put all the mental illnesses together,
عندما تضع جميع الأمراض النفسية معا،
they account for roughly 15 percent
تمثل ما يقرب من 15 في المائة
of the total global burden of disease.
من إجمالي أمراض العالم
Indeed, mental illnesses are also very damaging
والواقع أن الأمراض النفسية أيضا مدمرة جداً
to people's lives, but beyond just the burden of disease,
لحياة الناس، لكن ما وراء مجرد عبء المرض،
let us consider the absolute numbers.
دعونا ننظر في الأرقام.
The World Health Organization estimates
تشير تقديرات "منظمة الصحة العالمية"
that there are nearly four to five hundred million people
أن هناك ما يقرب من 400 إلى 500 مليون شخص
living on our tiny planet
على كوكبنا الصغير
who are affected by a mental illness.
الذين يصابون بمرض نفسي.
Now some of you here
الآن البعض منكم هنا
look a bit astonished by that number,
يندهش من هذا العدد،
but consider for a moment the incredible diversity
ولكن باعتبار التنوع الهائل
of mental illnesses, from autism and intellectual disability
للأمراض النفسية، من التوحّد والإعاقة الفكرية
in childhood, through to depression and anxiety,
في مرحلة الطفولة ومن خلال الاكتئاب والقلق
substance misuse and psychosis in adulthood,
وإساءة استعمال المواد المخدرة والذّهان في مرحلة البلوغ،
all the way through to dementia in old age,
حتى الخرف في مرحلة الشيخوخة،
and I'm pretty sure that each and every one us
وأنا متأكد أن كل واحد من
present here today can think of at least one person,
الحاضرين هنا اليوم يمكنه التفكير في شخص واحد على الأقل،
at least one person, who's affected by mental illness
شخص واحد فقط أَصيب بمرض نفسي
in our most intimate social networks.
من أقرب الأشخاص إلينا
I see some nodding heads there.
أرى بعض الناس يومئون هنا.
But beyond the staggering numbers,
ولكن ما وراء الأرقام المذهلة،
what's truly important from a global health point of view,
ما هو مهم حقاً من وجهة نظر الصحة العالمية،
what's truly worrying from a global health point of view,
وما هو حقاً مثير للقلق من وجهة نظر الصحة العالمية
is that the vast majority of these affected individuals
أن الغالبية العظمى من هؤلاء الأفراد المصابين
do not receive the care
لا يحصلون على الرعاية
that we know can transform their lives, and remember,
التي يمكن أن تغير حياتهم ويتذكرونها
we do have robust evidence that a range of interventions,
ولدينا أدلة قوية أن أنواعا كثيرة من أساليب العلاج
medicines, psychological interventions,
الأدوية والعلاج النفسي،
and social interventions, can make a vast difference.
والعلاج الاجتماعي، يمكن أن تحدث فرقا شاسعا.
And yet, even in the best-resourced countries,
ولكن، حتى في البلدان الغنية
for example here in Europe, roughly 50 percent
على سبيل المثال، هنا في أوروبا، ما يقرب من 50 في المائة
of affected people don't receive these interventions.
من الأشخاص المصابين لا يتلقون هذه العلاجات.
In the sorts of countries I work in,
في بعض البلدان التي أعمل فيها،
that so-called treatment gap
وهذا يطلق عليه الفجوة العلاجية
approaches an astonishing 90 percent.
وهو ما يقارب لدهشتنا الـ 90 في المائة.
It isn't surprising, then, that if you should speak
فإنه ليس من المستغرب، إذن، أنه إذا كان ينبغي أن تتحدث
to anyone affected by a mental illness,
لأي شخص من المصابين بمرض نفسي،
the chances are that you will hear stories
فهناك احتمالات بأن تسمع قصص
of hidden suffering, shame and discrimination
معاناة خفية وعار وتمييز
in nearly every sector of their lives.
في كل قطاع تقريبا في حياتهم.
But perhaps most heartbreaking of all
ولكن ربما الأكثر إفجاعا للجميع
are the stories of the abuse
قصص من إساءة المعاملة
of even the most basic human rights,
من أبسط حقوق الإنسان،
such as the young woman shown in this image here
مثل تلك المرأة الشابة الموضحة في هذه الصورة
that are played out every day,
التي يُتلاعب بها كل يوم،
sadly, even in the very institutions that were built to care
للأسف، حتى في نفس المؤسسات التي بنيت لترعى
for people with mental illnesses, the mental hospitals.
المرضى المصابين بأمراض نفسية، مستشفيات الأمراض النفسية.
It's this injustice that has really driven my mission
إنه الظلم الذي دفعني حقا
to try to do a little bit to transform the lives
إلى محاولة القيام بالقليل لتغيير حياة
of people affected by mental illness, and a particularly
الناس المصابين بالمرض النفسي، ولا سيما
critical action that I focused on is to bridge the gulf
الإجراءات الحاسمة التي ركزت على ملء الفجوة
between the knowledge we have that can transform lives,
بين المعرفة التي يمكن أن تغير حياة البشر
the knowledge of effective treatments, and how we actually
والمعرفة بعلاجات فعّالة، وكيف أننا فعلا
use that knowledge in the everyday world.
نستخدم تلك المعرفة في العالم كل يوم.
And an especially important challenge that I've had to face
ولاسيما تحديا هاما كان عليّ مواجهته
is the great shortage of mental health professionals,
وهو النقص الكبير في العاملين في مجال الصحة النفسية،
such as psychiatrists and psychologists,
مثل الأطباء النفسيين وعلماء النفس،
particularly in the developing world.
لا سيما في العالم النامي.
Now I trained in medicine in India, and after that
الآن تدربت في الطب في الهند، وبعد ذلك
I chose psychiatry as my specialty, much to the dismay
اخترت الطب النفسي كتخصص، والذي أفزع
of my mother and all my family members who
والدتي وجميع أفراد عائلتي الذين
kind of thought neurosurgery would be
فكّروا أن جراحة الأعصاب
a more respectable option for their brilliant son.
خيار أفضل لابنهم الرائع.
Any case, I went on, I soldiered on with psychiatry,
أيًا كان، أكملت طريقي وتخصصت في الطب النفسي
and found myself training in Britain in some of
ووجدت نفسي أتدرب في بريطانيا في أحد
the best hospitals in this country. I was very privileged.
أفضل المستشفيات في هذا البلد. كنت متميزًا جداً.
I worked in a team of incredibly talented, compassionate,
عملت في فريق من الموهوبين ويتّسمون بالرأفة
but most importantly, highly trained, specialized
ولكن الأهم من ذلك، متخصصون ومحترفون
mental health professionals.
من العاملين بالصحة النفسية.
Soon after my training, I found myself working
ووجدت نفسي أعمل مباشرة بعد التدريب
first in Zimbabwe and then in India, and I was confronted
أولاً في زمبابوي، ومن ثم في الهند، وواجهت
by an altogether new reality.
واقعا جديد تماما.
This was a reality of a world in which there were almost no
وكان الواقع أنه تقريبا لا يوجد
mental health professionals at all.
متخصصون في مجال الطب النفسي مطلقا
In Zimbabwe, for example, there were just about
ففي زمبابوي، على سبيل المثال، كان هناك فقط حوالي
a dozen psychiatrists, most of whom lived and worked
عشرات الأطباء النفسيين، معظمهم يعيشون ويعملون
in Harare city, leaving only a couple
في مدينة هراري، تاركين فقط القليل
to address the mental health care needs
لتلبية احتياجات الرعاية الصحية النفسية
of nine million people living in the countryside.
لـ 9 مليون من السكان الذين يعيشون في الريف.
In India, I found the situation was not a lot better.
وفي الهند، وجدت أن الوضع لم يكن أفضل بكثير.
To give you a perspective, if I had to translate
لأعطيكم الصورة الأكبر، إذا اضطررت لترجمة
the proportion of psychiatrists in the population
نسبة الأطباء النفسيين للسكان
that one might see in Britain to India,
بين بريطانيا و الهند،
one might expect roughly 150,000 psychiatrists in India.
قد تتوقع أن هناك 150,000 طبيب نفسي في الهند.
In reality, take a guess.
خمنوا ما هو الواقع !
The actual number is about 3,000,
العدد الفعلي هو حوالي 3000،
about two percent of that number.
نحو اثنين في المئة من هذا الرقم المُتوقع
It became quickly apparent to me that I couldn't follow
اتضح لي أني لن أستطيع أن أتّبع
the sorts of mental health care models that I had been trained in,
نماذج الرعاية الصحية النفسية التي تدربت عليها
one that relied heavily on specialized, expensive
والتي اعتمدت بشكل كبير على متخصصي
mental health professionals to provide mental health care
ومحترفي مجال الصحة النفسية ذوي الأجور المرتفعة لتوفير الرعاية الصحية النفسية
in countries like India and Zimbabwe.
في بلدان مثل الهند وزيمبابوي.
I had to think out of the box about some other model
واضطررت إلى التفكير خارج الصندوق في نموذج آخر
of care.
من الرعاية.
It was then that I came across these books,
ثم كان أن قرأت بعض هذه الكتب،
and in these books I discovered the idea of task shifting
وفي هذه الكتب اكتشفت فكرة "تحويل المهام"
in global health.
في مجال الصحة العالمية.
The idea is actually quite simple. The idea is,
والفكرة في الواقع بسيط جداً. الفكرة أنه
when you're short of specialized health care professionals,
عندما يكون هناك عجز في مهنيّي الرعاية الصحية المتخصصة،
use whoever is available in the community,
استخدم أي شخص موجود في المجتمع،
train them to provide a range of health care interventions,
دربهم لتوفير مجموعة من العلاجات الصحية
and in these books I read inspiring examples,
وقد وجدت أمثلة رائعة عندما كنت أقرأ في هذه الكتب
for example of how ordinary people had been trained
فعلى سبيل المثال كيف أن تدريب الناس العاديين
to deliver babies,
على الولادة
diagnose and treat early pneumonia, to great effect.
وتشخيص وعلاج الالتهاب الرئوي المبكر ذو أثر عظيم
And it struck me that if you could train ordinary people
وقد دُهشِت أنه إذا كان من الممكن تدريب الناس العاديين
to deliver such complex health care interventions,
للقيام بمثل هذه التدخلات المعقدة في الرعاية الصحية،
then perhaps they could also do the same
فيمكن أيضا عمل ذلك
with mental health care.
مع الرعاية الصحية النفسية.
Well today, I'm very pleased to report to you
اليوم، يسرني جداً أن أبلغكم
that there have been many experiments in task shifting
أن هناك العديد من التجارب في "تحويل المهام"
in mental health care across the developing world
في مجال الرعاية الصحية النفسية في العالم النامي
over the past decade, and I want to share with you
على مدى العقد الماضي، وأريد أن أشارك معكم
the findings of three particular such experiments,
نتائج ثلاثة تجارب خاصة
all three of which focused on depression,
الثلاثة تجارب تركّز على الاكتئاب،
the most common of all mental illnesses.
المرض الأكثر شيوعا في الطب النفسي
In rural Uganda, Paul Bolton and his colleagues,
في المناطق الريفية في أوغندا، عبر توظيف "بول بولتون" وزملائه،
using villagers, demonstrated that they could deliver
القرويين، اثبت أنه يمكن تقديم
interpersonal psychotherapy for depression
العلاج النفسي للمصابين بالاكتئاب
and, using a randomized control design,
وباستخدام تصميم "التحكم العشوائي"
showed that 90 percent of the people receiving
أظهروا أن 90 في المائة من الأشخاص الذين يتلقون
this intervention recovered as compared
هذا العلاج تم شفاؤهم بالمقارنة
to roughly 40 percent in the comparison villages.
مع حوالي 40 في المائة في القرى المجهزة.
Similarly, using a randomized control trial in rural Pakistan,
وبالمثل، باستخدام "التحكم العشوائي" في مناطق باكستان الريفية،
Atif Rahman and his colleagues showed
أظهر "عاطف رحمان" وزملاؤه
that lady health visitors, who are community maternal
أن الزائرات الصحية، اللاتي يُعتبرن من ضمن
health workers in Pakistan's health care system,
عمال الصحة في نظام الرعاية الصحية في باكستان،
could deliver cognitive behavior therapy for mothers
يمكنهن تقديم العلاج السلوكي المعرفي للأمهات
who were depressed, again showing dramatic differences
اللاتي أُصِبنَ بالاكتئاب، ومرة أخرى تظهر الاختلافات الهائلة
in the recovery rates. Roughly 75 percent of mothers
في معدلات الشفاء. ما يقرب من 75 في المائة الأمهات
recovered as compared to about 45 percent
اللاتي تم شفائهن بالمقارنة مع حوالي 45 في المئة
in the comparison villages.
في القرى المجهزة.
And in my own trial in Goa, in India, we again showed
وفي التجربة الخاصة بي في غوا، في الهند، أظهرنا مرة أخرى
that lay counselors drawn from local communities
أن وضع المستشارين الذين ينتمون إلى المجتمعات المحلية
could be trained to deliver psychosocial interventions
يمكن تدريبهم للقيام بالتدخلات النفسية
for depression, anxiety, leading to 70 percent
للاكتئاب، والقلق، مما أظهر نسبة 70 في المائة
recovery rates as compared to 50 percent
معدلات شفاء مقارنة بنسبة 50 في المائة
in the comparison primary health centers.
في مراكز الرعاية الصحية الأولية المجهزة للمقارنة.
Now, if I had to draw together all these different
الآن، إذا كان لي أن أرسم جميع هذه التجارب المختلفة
experiments in task shifting, and there have of course
في "تحويل المهام"، وهناك بالطبع
been many other examples, and try and identify
العديد من الأمثلة الأخرى، وبمحاولة تحديد
what are the key lessons we can learn that makes
أهم الدروس الرئيسية التي يمكننا أن نتعلم منها
for a successful task shifting operation,
لإنجاح عملية "تحويل المهام"،
I have coined this particular acronym, SUNDAR.
و قد صِغت هذا المختصر، "SUNDAR".
What SUNDAR stands for, in Hindi, is "attractive."
وهو ما يعني باللغة الهندية، "جذابة".
It seems to me that there are five key lessons
يبدو لي أن هناك خمسة دروس رئيسية
that I've shown on this slide that are critically important
وقد أظهرتها في هذه الشريحة وهي مهمة جدا
for effective task shifting.
من أجل "تحويل مهام" فعّال.
The first is that we need to simplify the message
الأول أننا بحاجة إلى تبسيط الرسالة
that we're using, stripping away all the jargon
التي نستخدمها، وتجريد كل المصطلحات الصعبة
that medicine has invented around itself.
التي أحاط الطب بها نفسه.
We need to unpack complex health care interventions
ونحن بحاجة إلى فك تدخلات الرعاية الصحية المعقدة
into smaller components that can be more easily
إلى مكونات أصغر والتي يمكن نقلها
transferred to less-trained individuals.
بسهولة إلى الأفراد الأقل تدريبا.
We need to deliver health care, not in large institutions,
ونحن بحاجة لتقديم الرعاية الصحية، لا في المؤسسات الكبيرة،
but close to people's homes, and we need to deliver
ولكن أقرب إلى بيوت الناس، ونحن بحاجة إلى تقديم
health care using whoever is available and affordable
الرعاية الصحية باستخدام كل من هو متاح
in our local communities.
في مجتمعاتنا المحلية.
And importantly, we need to reallocate the few specialists
والأهم من ذلك، نحن بحاجة إلى إعادة توزيع الأخصائيين القليلين
who are available to perform roles
الذين يقومون بعدة أدوار
such as capacity-building and supervision.
مثل بناء القدرات والإشراف عليها.
Now for me, task shifting is an idea
الآن بالنسبة لي، "تحويل المهام" هي فكرة
with truly global significance,
مهمة جدا عالميا
because even though it has arisen out of the
لأنه حتى على الرغم من أنها نشأت من
situation of the lack of resources that you find
حالة من الافتقار إلى الموارد التي تجدها
in developing countries, I think it has a lot of significance
في البلدان النامية، وأعتقد أن لها الكثير من الأهمية
for better-resourced countries as well. Why is that?
للبلدان الغنيّة كذلك. لم ذلك؟
Well, in part, because health care in the developed world,
حسنا، في جزء منه، لأن الرعاية الصحية في العالم المتقدم،
the health care costs in the [developed] world,
تكاليف الرعاية الصحية في العالم المتقدم،
are rapidly spiraling out of control, and a huge chunk
تتصاعد بسرعة وتخرج من السيطرة، وجزء ضخم
of those costs are human resource costs.
من هذه التكاليف هي تكاليف الموارد البشرية.
But equally important is because health care has become
ولكن بنفس القدر من الأهمية، لأن الرعاية الصحية أصبحت
so incredibly professionalized that it's become very remote
ذات طابع مِهَني بحت وأصبحت بعيدة
and removed from local communities.
وتمت إزالتها من المجتمعات المحلية.
For me, what's truly sundar about the idea of task shifting,
بالنسبة لي، ماهية "sundar" حقاً هي فكرة "تحويل المهام"،
though, isn't that it simply makes health care
رغم ذلك، ليست ببساطة أنه يجعل الرعاية الصحية
more accessible and affordable but that
أكثر وبتكلفة ميسورة لكنها
it is also fundamentally empowering.
أيضا أساس للتمكين.
It empowers ordinary people to be more effective
فإنها تمكّن الناس العاديين ليكونوا أكثر فعالية
in caring for the health of others in their community,
في العناية بصحة الآخرين في مجتمعهم،
and in doing so, to become better guardians
وفي القيام بذلك، يصبحوا أكثر اهتماما
of their own health. Indeed, for me, task shifting
بصحتهم هم. وفي الواقع، بالنسبة لي، "تحويل المهام"
is the ultimate example of the democratization
مثال على إضفاء الطابع الديمقراطي
of medical knowledge, and therefore, medical power.
على المعارف الطبية، وبالتالي، السلطة الطبية.
Just over 30 years ago, the nations of the world assembled
فقط منذ 30 عاما اجتمعت دول العالم
at Alma-Ata and made this iconic declaration.
في "ألما-آتا" وأصدروا هذا الإعلان المبدع.
Well, I think all of you can guess
حسنا، أعتقد أنه يمكنكم تخمين
that 12 years on, we're still nowhere near that goal.
أنه بعد 12 عاماً، لا نزال بعيدين عن هذا الهدف
Still, today, armed with that knowledge
ولكن، اليوم أصبحنا مسلحين بتلك المعرفة
that ordinary people in the community
أن الناس العاديين في المجتمع
can be trained and, with sufficient supervision and support,
يمكن أن يكونوا مدرَّبين، ومع إشراف كاف ودعم،
can deliver a range of health care interventions effectively,
يمكن تقديم مجموعة من تدخلات الرعاية الصحية على نحو فعال،
perhaps that promise is within reach now.
ولعل هذا الوعد في متناول اليد الآن.
Indeed, to implement the slogan of Health for All,
وفي الواقع، لتطبيق شعار الصحة للجميع،
we will need to involve all
سوف نحتاج إلى إشراك الجميع
in that particular journey,
في تلك الرحلة الخاصة،
and in the case of mental health, in particular we would
وبالذات في حالة الصحة النفسية
need to involve people who are affected by mental illness
سنحتاج إلى إشراك الناس الذين يتأثرون بالمرض النفسي
and their caregivers.
ومن يقدمون الرعاية لهم.
It is for this reason that, some years ago,
ولهذا السبب تأسست -منذ عدة سنوات-
the Movement for Global Mental Health was founded
"حركة الصحة النفسية العالمية"
as a sort of a virtual platform upon which professionals
كمنصة من نوع ما تساعد المهنيين
like myself and people affected by mental illness
مثلي والأشخاص المتأثرين بمرض نفسي
could stand together, shoulder-to-shoulder,
للوقوف معا، كتفا إلى كتف،
and advocate for the rights of people with mental illness
والدعوة لحقوق الأشخاص المصابين بمرض نفسي
to receive the care that we know can transform their lives,
للحصول على الرعاية التي نعرف أنها ستحوّل حياتهم
and to live a life with dignity.
وأن يعيشوا حياة كريمة.
And in closing, when you have a moment of peace or quiet
وفي الختام، عندما يكون لديك لحظة من السلام أو الهدوء
in these very busy few days or perhaps afterwards,
وفي هذه الأيام المشغولة جدا أو حتى بعد ذلك
spare a thought for that person you thought about
فكّر في ذلك الشخص
who has a mental illness, or persons that you thought about
من لديه مرض نفسي، أو فكّر في أولئك الأشخاص
who have mental illness,
الذين لديهم مرض نفسي،
and dare to care for them. Thank you. (Applause)
وفكّر في العناية بهم. شكرا. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)